Inventory of the National Cattlemen’s Association records, 1898-2018
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
National Cattlemen’s Association records
1898-2018
National Cattlemen’s Association (U.S.)
01713
404.41 cubic ft. (719 boxes) + 23.04 GB
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Business files, correspondence, financial records, photographs, and publications of this national organization of cattlemen.
History of the National Cattlemen’s Association
The origins of the National Cattlemen’s Association go back to January 1898, when a meeting of cattle, sheep, goat, swine, and horse growers was held in Denver, Colorado to consider forming a national organization to represent and defend the interests of livestock producers. At this meeting, the National Live Stock Growers Association was formed and John W. Springer became its first president. The organization changed its name to the National Live Stock Association in 1900.
In 1905, a group of cattle and sheep growers protested the presence of meat packers, railroad representatives and others allied but not directly involved with the livestock industry in the National Live Stock Association, and broke away to form the American Stock Growers Association. However, the two organizations reunited to form the American National Live Stock Association in 1906.
Between 1906 and 1953, the market for horses declined and sheep and swine growers gradually drifted away to form their own national organizations, leaving behind a membership consisting primarily of cattlemen and cattlemen’s associations. In recognition of this, the American National Live Stock Association changed its name to the American National Cattlemen’s Association (ANCA) in 1953.
In 1977, ANCA merged with the National Livestock Feeders Association, and changed its name to the National Cattlemen’s Association (NCA). By this time, the NCA represented a membership from all facets of the cattle industry. In 1996, NCA merged with the National Beef Council to form the National Cattlemen’s Beef Association (NCBA).
Scope and Content
The National Cattlemen’s Association Records contain the business files, correspondence, financial records, photographs, and publications documenting the activities and history of the organization. Series I concerns the activities of the Board of Directors. Series II contains the files of individual NCA executives. Series III contains department files and Series IV documents the activities of the NCA’s permanent and special committees. Series V consists of files regarding member associations.
Series VI, the largest series of the collection, contains the subject files, which concern issues, people, and organizations of interest to the NCA. Series VII consists of materials regarding the NCA’s annual conventions and mid-year meetings. Series VIII documents legal matters involving the NCA and Series IX contains financial files. Series X and XI consist of administrative files and general correspondence respectively. Series XII contains copies of mimeographed documents produced by the organization.
Series XIII consists of photographic materials, including photographs, slides, transparencies, and negatives. Series XIV contains publications produced by the NCA, including books, periodicals, and newsletters and also contains the files documenting their production and publication. Series XV consists of miscellaneous materials, including clippings, press releases, reports, and statements. Series XVI holds the audio-visual materials, which consist of audio recordings and motion pictures. Series XVII contains the oversized materials, which includes of scrapbooks and financial ledgers.
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
There are no other known archival collections created by the National Cattlemen’s Association at the date of processing.
This material was received from the National Cattlemen's Beef Association, the National Cattlemen’s Association, and Roxaine L. Swena from 1965-2016, The University of Montana, Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library in 2018, and Kendal Frazier in 2020.
Access Terms
American National Cowbelles.; Cattle--United States.; Cattle breeders--United States.; Cattle trade--United States.; Livestock--Societies, etc.; Range management--United States.;;; Sound recordings.; Minutes.; Photographs.;;; National Cattlemen’s Beef Association (U.S.)
Agriculture and Natural Resources; Ranching; Business, Industry, Labor, and Commerce; Politics, Government, and Law; Clubs and Societies
- Board of Directors Files, Series I.
  This series documents the activities of Board of Directors. Materials found in this series include correspondence, minutes, reports, resolutions, and action plans.
  - Articles of Incorporation & By-laws, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Background Materials/Information, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Committee Lists, 1962-1963, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1964, 1967-1968, 1980-1985, 1987 (Box 1, Folders 5-12)
  - Fact Sheet, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Financial Statements, 1981-1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Legal Documents, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Marketing Plans, Fiscal Year 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Member Lists, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1962, 1980, 1984-1989 (Box 2, Folders 6-11)
  - Officer Lists, 1968, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Press Releases, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Proceedings, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Proposed Priority Issue Action Plans, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Reports, 1981, 1987 (Box 3, Folders 2-4)
  - Resolutions, 1964, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Suggested Board Appointments, 1961-1964 (Box 3, Folders 6-7)
  - Suggested Board and Committee Appointments, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Suggested Committee Appointments, 1961-1964 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Meeting Room Reservations, October 6, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Board of Director Minutes (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Board of Directors (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Board Nominations (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors Files: Proceedings, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors Files: Board of Directors Meetings, Proceedings, January 1962 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Board of Directors Files: Board of Directors Special Meeting, Portersville, CA, Proceedings, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Board of Directors, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Summer Meeting, Denver, CO, Minutes and Proceedings, July 23-24, 1968 (Box 5, Folders 1-3)
  - Minutes, 1962-1968, 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folders 4-5)
  - Board of Directors (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Board of Directors Lists, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Board of Governors and staff, 1996-1997 (Box 700)
- Executive Files, Series II.
  This series contains the personal files of individual NCA executives. It consists mostly of correspondence, but also contains materials such as biographies, press releases, and reports.
  - Arney, Frank, 1978-1979, 1982 (Box 6, Folders 1-4)
  - Arney, Frank, (bound reports), 1976 (Box 688)
  - Arnold, Thomas F., 1955-1958 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Berglund, Roger, 1982 (Box 6, Folders 6-8)
  - Berry, W.T. “Dub,”, 1982 (Box 6, Folders 9-12)
  - Blaine, Charles E., 1956, 1959-1960 (Box 6, Folders 13-14)
  - Blaine, Charles E., 1960-1961 (Box 7, Folders 1-7)
  - Blaine, Charles E., 1961-1962 (Box 8, Folders 1-6)
  - Blaine, Charles E., 1963-1965 (Box 9, Folders 1-7)
  - Blaine, Charles E., 1966-1969, undated (Box 10, Folders 1-7)
  - Boice, Frank, 1952-1968 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Boice, Henry, 1956-1958 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Booth, Mrs. Leavitt, undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Brewster, Lyman, 1955-1958 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Brownfield, A. D., 1955-1957 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Burghart, Mrs. Robert A., 1958 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Campbell, Dudley T., 1964 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Carlson, Merlyn, 1980 (Box 11, Folders 8-12)
  - Carlson, Merlyn, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Carpenter, Farrington, 1953 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Carson, John, 1982 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Champ, Frederick P., 1953-1957 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Collins, Don C., 1955-1960, undated (Box 12, Folders 5-11)
  - Cook, Tom, 1977 (Box 12, Folders 12-13)
  - Cook, Tom, 1977-1980 (Box 13, Folders 1-10)
  - Cook, Tom, 1980-1982 (Box 14, Folders 1-5)
  - Cunningham, Kirby, 1982 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Dahl, Jack, 1986-1987 (Box 14, Folders 7-11)
  - Dahl, Jack, 1987-1988 (Box 15, Folders 1-3)
  - DeGraff, Herell, 1959-1961 (Box 15, Folders 4-11)
  - DeGraff, Herell, 1960-1962, undated (Box 16, Folders 1-6)
  - Dressler, Fred, 1959-1963 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Elver, J. Burton, 1982 (Box 16, Folders 8-11)
  - Farr, William D., 1955-1958, 1969, 1977 (Box 16, Folders 12-14)
  - Frazier, Kendal:
    - Audio/Visual materials:
      - Video - The Guide to Ground Beef (VHS), 1994 (Box 717)
      - Video - History Matters "A Story of Change" (3 copies - VHS), 1987 (Box 717)
      - Video - Shaping a Nation (3 copies-VHS), 1987 (Box 717)
    - Board meetings - agendas and minutes, 1992-2014 (Box 712)
    - Convention Files:
      - 1997 Annual Convention (Box 712)
      - 1998 Summer Conference (Box 712)
      - 1999 Annual Convention (Box 712)
      - 2008 Annual Convention - meeting agendas (Box 712)
      - 2008 Summer Conference - meeting agendas (Box 712)
      - 2009 Convention - awards luncheon, policy division forum, HUDDLE (Box 712)
      - 2009 Summer Conference - schedule, general sessions 1-2, July 2009 (Box 712)
      - 2010 Annual Convention - OGS 2 (Box 712)
    - Committee Files:
      - Advertising Committee meeting - joint NCBA/CBB, August 2000 (Box 712)
      - Affiliate Planning meetings - agenda, 2008-2009 (Box 712)
      - Committee Leadership meeting - agenda, 2009 (Box 712)
      - Executive Committee - meeting agendas and handbook, 2008-2018 (Box 712)
      - Information Committee - agenda and minutes, 1997-1998 (Box 712)
      - Membership meeting - agenda, 2009 (Box 712)
      - Nominating Committee, 2009 (Box 712)
      - NCBA Officer meetings - agendas, 2008 (Box 712)
      - SBC (State Beef Council) - planning meetings and director orientation, 2008-2014 (Box 712)
    - Correspondence and Memos, 1985-89 (Box 712)
    - Financial Files: Budgets (National Cattleman's Association), 1991-1994 (Box 712)
    - Legal Files:
      - Predator/EPA case, 1975-1976 (Box 712)
      - Tax Case, 1971-1973 (Box 712)
      - Sagebrush Feeders Inc., et. al vs. Safeway Stores Inc. (Lubbock, Texas suit), 1977 (Box 712)
      - U.S. of America v. S&H Central Meat Packers Inc., 1977 (Box 712)
      - Anti-Trust - Miscellaneous, 1975 (Box 712)
      - Anti-Trust - Sept., 1977, A.D. Lee et. al. vs. Safeway Stores Inc. (Box 712)
      - Hitch, et al, v. A&P Safeway, Krogers, 1975 (Box 712)
      - Golob & Sons Inc., et al vs. Shaake Packing Co. & Safeway Stores Inc., et al, 1962-1969 (Box 713)
      - Bray, et al v. Safeway's - Anti-Trust, 1974-1975 (Box 713)
      - CPIRGY National Meat Packers Inc., civil action #400708, 1977 (Box 713)
      - Rath vs. Becker and General Mills vs. Jones, 1976 (Box 713)
      - Jones & Gurrero vs. USDA, 1976 (Box 713)
      - EPA - Manure, 1973-1976 (Box 713)
    - Media, Press, and Promotion:
      - Articles, 1990-2003 (Box 713)
      - Articles (newspapers) - Mad Cow Beef Recall, 2003-2004 (Box 719)
      - Fact Sheets, 1985-1997 (Box 713)
      - Media analysis and results (CARMA) - NCBA (National Cattlemen's Beef Association), 1990-2000 (Box 713)
      - Media guide (NCBA), 2011 (Box 713)
      - Newsletters: Beef Business Bulletin, 1990-1996 (Box 713)
      - Newsletters: The Beef Brief: Issues and Trends in the Cattle Industry, 1991-1996 (Box 713)
      - News Releases, 1985-1996 (Box 713-714)
      - Promotion - Beef Butcher Block card game, 1980 (Box 714)
      - Promotion - Hot Dogs and Pork, 1966 and undated (Box 714)
      - Reports - Media Usage Among Farmers, February 1989 (Box 714)
    - Membership (NCA):
      - NCA membership surveys, 1984 (Box 714)
      - Membership brochures and reports, 1985-1990 (Box 714)
      - Membership Policy Ballot, 2008-2011 (Box 714)
    - National Live Stock and Meat Board: 43rd- 66th Annual Reports, 1965-1988 (Box 716)
    - National Live Stock and Meat Board: Financial Statements, 1964-1965 (Box 716)
    - Photographs: Exhibit units, 400 Historical file (1) (prints), 1965-1979 (Box 714)
    - Photographs: School Lunch (glass lantern slides), 1950-1960 (Box 718)
    - Presentations: Miscellaneous and "What is NCBA?", 1999-2002 (Box 714)
    - Publications:
      - Miscellaneous, 1963-2015 (Box 714)
      - Historic publications, 1914-1991 (Box 714)
      - Assessment of the Cattle and Hog Industries, 2001 (Box 714)
      - Growth of a Force: 25 Years of the Meat Board, 1963-1988 (Box 714)
      - National Cattlemen Directions magazine, June/July 2000 (Box 714)
      - Federation of State Beef Councils: Strong State/National Partnership - investor reports, 2008 and 2010 (Box 714)
      - Beef USA packet, 1999-2000 (Box 714)
      - NCBA 2003 Marketing Opportunities (Box 714)
      - NCBA Driving Demand: 2004 Media Opportunities (Box 714)
      - Progress in Research - National Livestock and Meat Board, 1990 (Box 714)
      - NCBA 2001 Research annual report (Box 714)
    - Reports - miscellaneous, 1988-1996 (Box 715)
    - Resolutions, 1999 (Box 715)
    - Scrapbook: Monfort, 1987-1993 (Box 719)
    - Speeches, 1987-2009 (Box 715)
    - Strategic planning:
      - NCA Strategic plans, 1987-1993 (Box 715)
      - Beef Promotion and Research Board, draft strategic plan, June 1990 (Box 715)
      - Industry Information annual plans, 1993-1994 (Box 715)
      - NCA A Management Review of the Association, Executive Summary, August 1983 (Box 715)
      - NCA Procedures for Industry Information, 1989 (Box 715)
      - Evaluation of the NCBA, prepared by Thomas J. Hoban, PH.D., N.C. State University, 1998 (Box 715)
      - Reports and research, 2000-2010 (Box 715)
    - Subject Files:
      - 1988 Retorle campaign (715)
      - Booze Allaw, undated (715)
      - Image improvement ideas, 1988-1989 (715)
      - BPRIA (Beef Promotion and Research), 1986 (715)
      - Nutrition team, 1997 (715)
      - Results Presentation 2001-KF demand strategies (2 CDs), 2001-2003 (715 and Digital, ahcdm_01713_022-023)
      - National Beef Quality audit, 2011 (715)
      - Summer Grilling (CD), 2006 (715 and Digital, ahcdm_01713_024)
      - FMI tour, 1987 (715)
      - "War on Fat" media tours, 1991 (715)
      - Steinman, David, 1990 (715)
      - Farm Policy, 1986 (715)
      - Futures, 1988 (715)
      - Drought, 1988 (715)
      - Inventory, 1987 (715)
      - Hot Fat trimming, 1988 (715)
      - Imports, 1979 (715)
      - Speeches, 1985 (715)
      - Farm Credit, 1987 (715)
      - Earth First, 1989 (715)
      - Report Card Seattle/Atlanta, 1990 (715)
      - New Range Wars, 1991 (715)
      - Arizona--Today Show, 1990 (715)
      - Diet/Health, 1987 (715)
      - DES, 1979 (715)
      - Dairy Program, 1988 (715)
      - Richard McDonald Leadership Institute, 2013 (715)
      - Professional Development workshop, 2019 (715)
      - NCA membership structure, 1987 (715)
      - Effects of Meat Recalls on Futures Market Prices, September 2001 (715)
      - A Report and Recommendations for a Continuing Educational Program for the National Livestock and Meat Board, November 12, 1968 (715)
      - Issues update: A Summary of Key Issues Affecting the Beef Industry, May/June 1995 (715)
      - U.S. Hispanic Market Trends, September 2002 (715)
      - Beef Demand Determinants, report prepared by Ted C. Schroeder, Thomas L. Marsh, and James Mintert, January 27, 2000 (715)
      - The Real Economics of Beef Production, June 30, 1992 (715)
      - The LaCosta Conference on "Cattle on the Land:" Environmental implications of Beef production, June 8, 1992 (715)
  - Goldesberry, Sally, 1982 (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Guthrie, John H., 1954-1967 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Hall, Radford, 1955-1959 (Box 17, Folders 2-3)
  - Hansen, Chifford, 1955 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Hart, Stephen H., 1954-1958, 1961-1968, undated (Box 17, Folders 5-7)
  - Helming, William C., 1963, 1966 (Box 17, Folders 8-10)
  - Helming, William C., 1967 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Hinkhouse, F.W., 1956-1958 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Hyatt, Sam C., 1953-1958 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - House, Bill, 1968-1969 (Box 18, Folders 4-6)
  - Jones, Bill, 1980s (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Kendall, Don, 1983-1984 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Keogh, Brooks, 1961-1963 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Keogh, Brooks, 1964-1967 (Box 19, Folders 1-4)
  - Liggett, Lyle, 1955-1957 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Lynam, Mrs. O.W., undated (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Marble, John M., 1954-1958, 1960-1963, undated (Box 19, Folders 7-10)
  - Marble, Peter E., Region VI, 1968-1969 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Mayer, A. Kiefer, 1954, 1956 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - McDougal, Harvey A., undated (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - McDougal, Richard S., 1976-1978 (Box 20, Folders 4-13)
  - McDougal, Richard S., 1978-1979 (Box 21, Folders 1-7)
  - McMillan, C.W., 1956 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Meetz, John, 1984 (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Meetz, John, 1984-1986 (Box 22, Folders 1-7)
  - Meetz, John, 1984-1988 (Box 23, Folders 1-6)
  - Michieli, Ronald A., 1981-1982 (Box 23, Folders 7-8)
  - Michieli, Ronald A., 1982 (Box 24, Folders 1-2)
  - Milburn, G.R., 1958-1961, undated (Box 24, Folders 3-5)
  - Mitchell, Hayes, 1956-1957 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Mockler, Frank, 1956-1957 (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Mollin, F.E., 1948-1958 (Box 24, Folders 8-11)
  - Nelson, Don, 1981-1982 (Box 25, Folders 1-9)
  - Newmann, Carl, 1957, 1961, undated (Box 25, Folders 10-11)
  - Radebaugh, Cushman, 1956-1961 (Box 25, Folder 12)
  - Radebaugh, Cushman, 1962-1964, 1966 (Box 26, Folders 1-4)
  - Riley, Jim, 1979-1980, 1982 (Box 26, Folders 5-7)
  - Rogers, Alan, 1956-1957 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Russell, Hubbard, 1955-1958 (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - Russell, Joe, 1956-1957 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Shoemaker, E.H., Region III, 1968 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Sinclair, F.H., 1951-1952 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Smith, JoAnn, 1979-1986 (Box 27, Folders 4-12)
  - Smith, JoAnn, 1979-1987 (Box 28, Folders 1-5)
  - Spencer, George S., 1977-1978 (Box 28, Folders 6-11)
  - Spencer, George S., 1978-1979 (Box 29, Folders 1-7)
  - Spencer, George S., 1980 (Box 30, Folders 1-6)
  - Spencer, George S., 1979, 1980 (Box 31, Folders 1-2)
  - Strackbein, O.R., 1955-1957, 1960-1962 (Box 31, Folders 3-4)
  - Swan, Bill, 1980-1982 (Box 31, Folders 5-8)
  - Taggart, Lloyd, undated (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Taylor, Lot, undated (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - Taylor, Jay, 1952-1957 (Box 32, Folders 3-8)
  - Thorp, Russell, 1955-1956 (Box 32, Folders 9-11)
  - Thorp, Russell, 1957-1958 (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - Trotman, John, Region II, 1968 (Box 33, Folder 2)
  - Waldrip, W.J., 1982-1984 (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - Washburn, Sam, 1981-1984 (Box 33, Folders 4-10)
  - Washburn, Sam, 1980s (Box 34, Folders 1-6)
  - Watt, Joe, Region V, 1968 (Box 34, Folder 7)
  - Weber, John, 1983-1985 (Box 34, Folders 8-12)
  - White, Eldon, 1979 (Box 34, Folder 13)
  - White, Eldon, 1979-1980 (Box 35, Folders 1-7)
  - Spencer, G., 1976-1977 (Box 36, Folders 1-11)
  - Welch, John, 1976 (Box 36, Folders 12-13)
  - White, Dennis, 1976 (Box 36, Folders 14-19)
  - Cook, Tom, 1975 (Box 36, Folders 20-25)
  - Creer, John, 1971, 1973 (Box 36, Folders 26-27)
  - Farr, W.D., 1970-1971 (Box 36, Folders 28-30)
  - Finney, Wray, 1971-1974 (Box 36, Folder 31)
  - House, Bill, President, 1970 (Box 36, Folder 32)
  - House, Jim, 1974 (Box 36, Folder 33)
  - Pellet, T., 1975 (Box 37, Folders 1-10)
  - Spencer, G., 1975 (Box 37, Folders 11-19)
  - Tooker, J., 1975-1976 (Box 37, Folders 20-36)
  - Trotman, John, 1970-1974 (Box 37, Folders 37-38)
  - Rolston, Bob, 1975-1976 (Box 37, Folders 39-42)
  - Cook, Tom, “Executive Stud Award,”, 1973 (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - Riley, James W., 1968-1969, 1974-1982 (Box 38, Folders 2-19)
  - Riley, James W., 1975-1981 (Box 39, Folders 1-13)
  - Riley, James W., Energy Committee, 1981 (Box 39, Folders 14-19)
  - Riley, James W., NASA Hydrology Program, 1979-1981 (Box 39, Folders 20-24)
  - Riley, James W., NASA Hydrology Program, 1979-1981 (Box 40, Folders 1-5)
  - Washburn, Sam, 1979-1981 (Box 40, Folder 6)
  - Strackbein, O.R., 1953-1958 (Box 40, Folders 7-9)
  - Cunningham, Kirby, 1976-1977 (Box 40, Folders 10-23)
  - Elkins, Chuck, 1976-1977 (Box 40, Folders 24-31)
  - Cook, Tom, 1976 (Box 41, Folders 1-6)
  - Elkins, Chuck, 1977 (Box 41, Folders 7-8)
  - Finney, Wray, 1975-1977 (Box 41, Folders 9-29)
  - Goulding, Evan, 1975-1976 (Box 41, Folders 30-34)
  - Kreutz, J., 1976-1977 (Box 41, Folder 35)
  - McDougal, 1976 (Box 41, Folder 36)
  - McMillan, C.W., 1967 (Box 41, Folder 37)
  - Pellet, T., 1976 (Box 41, Folders 38-39)
  - Berglund, Roger, 1974 (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - Cook, Tom, 1973 (Box 42, Folders 2-3)
  - Farn, W.D., Gift, 1971 (Box 42, Folder 4)
  - Radebaugh, Mrs. Cushman S., 1965 (Box 42, Folder 5)
  - Van Vleck, Gordon, 1973-1974 (Box 42, Folders 6-10)
  - White, Dennis, 1975 (Box 42, Folders 11-14)
  - Blaine, Charles E., 1970-1971 (Box 42, Folders 15-16)
  - Brock, J. Elmer, 1946-1947 (Box 42, Folder 17)
  - Finney, Wray, 1975 (Box 42, Folder 18)
  - Hughes, Dan, 1946-1948 (Box 42, Folder 19)
  - Metcalf, Vernon, 1947 (Box 42, Folder 20)
  - Spencer, G., 1974 (Box 42, Folder 21)
  - Van Vleck, Gordon, 1975-1976 (Box 42, Folders 22-24)
  - White, Eldon, 1982 (Box 42, Folder 25)
  - Wittig, Fred, 1955-1957 (Box 42, Folder 26)
  - Wright, William B., 1955-1963 (Box 42, Folder 27)
- Department Files, Series III.
  This series concerns the activities of various NCA departments, particularly the Policy Development and the Traffic and Transportation Department respectively. Materials found in this series consist chiefly of correspondence and reports.
  - Economic Services-Riley, Jim, 1980 (Box 43, Folders 1-3)
  - Marketing Department, Marketing Plans-1987-1988, Fiscal Year (Box 43, Folder 4)
  - Membership Department, 1977 (Box 43, Folder 5)
  - Policy Development Department, 1979 (Box 43, Folders 6-10)
  - Policy Development Department, 1979 (Box 44, Folders 1-7)
  - Policy Development Department, 1979 (Box 45, Folders 1-7)
  - Traffic and Transportation Department, 1937-1948 (Box 46, Folders 1-12)
  - Policy Development Department, 1979-1980 (Box 47, Folders 1-2)
  - Traffic and Transportation Department, 1929-1936, 1960 (Box 47, Folders 3-12)
  - Traffic and Transportation Department, 1949-1960 (Box 48, Folders 1-12)
  - Traffic and Transportation Department, 1961-1963 (Box 49, Folders 1-3)
  - Washington Bureau, 1966, 1968 (Box 49, Folder 4)
  - R.R. Litigation, Correspondence, Calvin Blaine, undated (Box 49, Folder 5)
  - Transportation, 1975 (Box 49, Folder 6)
  - Freight Audit, 1973 (Box 49, Folder 7)
  - Washington Office, 1980 (Box 49, Folder 8)
  - Government, Washington D.C. Affairs, 1970 (Box 49, Folder 9)
- Committee Files, Series IV.
  This series documents the activities of the NCA’s permanent and temporary committees. Materials found in this series include correspondence, minutes, press releases, reports, resolutions, and action plans.
  - Affiliate Executive Officers Advisory Council, 1982 (Box 50, Folder 1)
  - Anaplasmosis Subcommittee, 1962-1968 (Box 50, Folders 2-6)
  - Animal Health Committee, 1967-1968 (Box 50, Folders 7-11)
  - Animal Health and Identification Committee-Subcommittees, 1980-1981 (Box 50, Folder 12-15)
  - Beef Grading Committee, 1956-1968 (Box 50, Folders 16-17)
  - Beef Grading Committee, 1955-1958, 1960-1962 (Box 51, Folders 1-7)
  - Beef Grading Committee, 1955-1968, undated (Box 52, Folders 1-11)
  - Beef Grading Committee, 1950-1968, undated (Box 53, Folders 1-6)
  - Beef Grading Committee, Animal Health Questionnaires, 1963 (Box 53, Folder 7)